Well, good morning, good
afternoon, and
good evening.
My name is Stratus
Cantunas, and I'm
one of your academic
medicine scholars.
Today, I'm gonna be
giving you all a lecture
on ischemic heart
disease part one, and Dr.
Murad will be following
up with part two.
Before we begin, I
just wanted to say a
special thank you
to all the previous
scholars who contributed
to this lecture
topic, but most
importantly, thank you to
Dr. Murad for allowing
me to collaborate
on and present this
lecture to you all.
So these are my session
objectives. I'm not
going to read them
to you but just take
your time and read them
through if you would
like personally I think
session objectives
are important and if
you have a good grasp
on these session
objectives I think you'll
have a good understanding
of this lecture
as a whole the only
thing I would like to
point out is number
three differentiate
stable angina from unstable
angina this lecture
won't really touch
upon unstable but when
you put my lecture in
conjunction with part
two given by Dr. Murad
you'll be able to
differentiate stable
angina from unstable
angina so on your
second pass through keep
that in mind so let's
begin with definitions
throughout my lecture
one of the most
important words you're
going to hear over and
over and over again
with this topic is
angina so angina pectoris
or just angina for
short refers to chest
discomfort that occurs
when myocardial oxygen
demand exceeds oxygen
supply in the context
of this lecture
we're going to use it
as just a fancy word
for heart induced
chest pain there are
different types of angina
they're stable, unstable,
vasospastic angina.
But like I said
before, in my lecture,
we're just going to
focus on stable and
vasospastic angina. And
part two, we'll touch
upon unstable angina.
So what is ischemic
heart disease?
And what is acute
coronary syndrome?
Ischemic heart disease,
also referred to
as coronary artery
disease, is a condition
associated with the
inadequate supply of
blood to the myocardium
due to obstruction
of the coronary arteries,
and this obstruction
is usually from
atherosclerosis. Acute
coronary syndrome
is an acute form of
ischemic heart disease
characterized by a
sudden and severe
decrease in blood flow to
the heart, causing
symptoms such as chest
pain and shortness
of breath. Therefore,
we say that acute
coronary syndrome is a
specific type of heart
condition that falls
under the broader
umbrella of ischemic heart
disease. Some key
differences we can see is
that ischemic heart
disease is a chronic
condition that can develop
gradually over years
while acute coronary
syndrome is a more sudden
and severe event.
Acute coronary syndrome
also represents a more
severe and immediate
threat to the heart
muscle compared to the
chronic nature of
ischemic heart disease and
ischemic heart disease
symptoms can be milder
ranging from angina
or even the absence
thereof while acute
coronary syndrome often
presents with severe
chest pain, shortness of
breath and potential
heart attack symptoms.
Essentially,
acute coronary syndrome
is a more acute
and severe manifestation
of the underlying
problem of reduced
blood flow and ischemic
heart disease. It's
important to note
that while all acute
coronary syndromes are
types of ischemic
heart disease, not all
ischemic heart diseases
are acute coronary
syndrome. Think of IHD
as a larger category
of problems involving
reduced blood
flow to the heart,
where IHD encompasses
conditions like stable
angina, unstable angina,
silent myocardial
ischemia, and acute
coronary syndrome is
one of the most severe
and urgent forms
within this category.
Acute coronary syndrome
is absolutely a
medical emergency requiring
immediate diagnosis
and treatment to
restore blood flow and
prevent further damage
to the heart, of which
will be covered in part
two of this lecture.
As far as the epidemiology
goes, I just wanted
to touch on this so that
everyone understands
the prevalence and
the real importance
of this topic. Coronary
heart disease is the
most common type of
heart disease and has
killed over 300,000 people
in 2022 alone. About
one in 20 adults age
20 and older have
coronary artery disease
and in 2022 about one
out of every five deaths
from cardiovascular
disease was among
adults younger than 65
years old. In fact there
was recently a study
that demonstrated by 2050
the global incidence,
prevalence, and deaths
of ischemic heart
disease were projected
to reach 67.3 million,
510 million, and 16
million respectively,
which shows an
increase in over
100% in each
incidence, prevalence,
and the deaths from 2021.
Moreover, these
results show
that the regions
with lower
sociodemographic
index, or an SDI,
bore a greater burden
of ischemic heart
disease than those with
higher sociodemographic
indexes, with men
having a higher
burden of ischemic heart
disease than women.
However, don't
really get too bogged
down with the details
of this. I'm not
going to test you on
this. I just think
it's super important
to really understand
the scope of ischemic
heart disease.
Let's move on to
the risk factors.
So understanding
the risk factors for
a disease is just
as important as
focusing on the treatment
and the solution
to a medical
condition. I split
them up into modifiable
and non-modifiable
to help with your
understanding.
But again, you don't
really need to memorize
this list. Just
looking at some of the
bullet points, they should
be self-explanatory,
right? Anything
that's going to cause
atherosclerotic plaque
buildup is going to be
a risk factor for
coronary artery disease
because it's going to
occlude the vessel and
reduce the myocardial
oxygen supply. So going
through the list on
the left of modifiable,
we're going to look
at cigarette smoke,
hypertension where
uncontrolled high blood
pressure can actually
damage the arteries
high cholesterol or
specifically high levels
of LDL the bad
cholesterol and low levels
of HDL or the good
cholesterol contribute
to plaque buildup in
arteries you'll see
diabetes which increases
the risk of ischemic
heart disease due to
hyperglycemia induced
endothelial damage
obesity because excess
body fat especially
around the abdomen has
been linked to a higher
risk of atherosclerosis,
high blood pressure,
high cholesterol,
and diabetes. Lack
of exercise because
physical inactivity
increases the risk of a
semitic heart disease
and associated conditions
again like obesity,
high blood pressure.
And then lastly you'll
see an unhealthy diet
or more specifically a
diet high in saturated
and trans fats, high
in salt and sugar
have also been linked to
an increase in the risk
of coronary artery
disease. The big one
I'd like to point out
and bolded is cigarette
smoking. Smoking is
actually the leading
preventable primary risk
factor for cardiovascular
disease and an
independent major risk
factor for coronary
heart disease
and cerebrovascular
disease. Among patients
with established
cardiovascular
disease, the risk of a
recurrent event is
increased among those who
continue to smoke
compared to those who do
not. So therefore,
quitting smoking is going
to be super, super,
super important. The
benefits of quitting
cigarette smoking and tobacco
use of any variety
are actually firmly
established in the
literature, but perhaps may
be lesser known and
accepted amongst the
general public. The cardiac
risk factors associated
with cigarette smoking
actually diminish
within a few years
after smoking cessation
and continue to fall
with increasing length
of time since quitting.
So it doesn't just
create an immediate
effect, but it actually
creates an effect over
the years. And this is
why we put such a
major emphasis on the
importance of counseling
on smoking cessation.
Lots of patients
will think like, hey,
I've been smoking for
20 years, so it doesn't
really make a difference
if I stop now,
right? But in actuality,
it does, and the
benefits are to be
seen in the years to
come, even if they're
on the older side.
Exposure to secondhand
smoke also increases
non-smokers' risk of
cardiovascular disease.
So if you have a
patient who has a spouse
that may smoke around
them, it's a very
high risk factor. so
we want to keep those
questions in the back
of our mind to ask.
With respect to risk
of cardiovascular
disease associated with
non-cigarette smoking,
such as like pipe
or cigar, smokeless
tobacco, vaping, the data
is somewhat less clear
regarding the risk.
Many studies have
shown an increased risk
associated, many have
shown not increased
risk, so it's important
to keep those questions
on you as well.
The rest of the risk
factors under the non
-modifiable on the
right, there's going to
be things that you
can't really change. For
example, men older
than 45 and women older
than 55 are generally
considered to have
an increased baseline
risk of cardiovascular
disease. Male compared
to females generally
have a higher risk.
Certain ethnicities
have a greater risk
than other ethnicities.
So keep these things
in mind as well. But
at the end of the
day, cigarette smoking
is absolutely terrible
for you and is
horrible in regards to
your coronary arteries.
So the pathogenesis
of coronary artery
disease has been
discussed in another
lecture, probably by
Dr. Plummer. However,
I still think it's
super important for
your board exam. So
I actually created a
GIF for you that
explains the process in
its entirety. And if
you look at the notes
underneath the slide,
I've written out
the explanation of
what's going on in
the GIF. If you'd
like to read these on
your own, please do
so on your own time.
So in front of you, I
have a case vignette
of a patient, and
we're going to use
this patient to kind
of break down what is
ischemic heart disease
throughout this
lecture. So when a
patient first arrives
in either emergency
department or your
family medicine office
or your urgent care,
wherever you're
working, you'll always
first start with a
chief complaint. Here,
we have a chief
complaint of chest pain.
So when a patient
presents with the chief
complaint of chest
pain, the first question
we must answer is how
do we define it? In
the initial assessment,
it's essential to
triage patients based
on the likelihood that
their symptoms are
attributable to myocardial
ischemia because with
any heart-related
complaint time is
always of the essence.
So back in 1970s the
Diamond Forrester
classification was
developed as a clinical tool
to assess the probability
that chest pain
was due to coronary
artery disease. The
system relied heavily on
symptom quality however
we now know that
symptom descriptions
alone are not enough and
modern decision making
incorporates things
such as age, ***,
cardiovascular risk
factors, diagnostic tools
such as the ECG or
troponin testing, which
I'll talk about later,
and validated clinical
risk scores like
the heart score. So
back in 2021, the
American Heart Association
and the American
College of Cardiologists
updated their guidance
to reflect these
broader considerations.
And this update, as you
see in front of you,
was designed to reduce
misdiagnoses,
particularly in women,
younger patients and
those with atypical
presentations to ensure
more accurate and timely
identification of
patients presenting with
chest pain. So as
you can see, now it's
split up into three
categories. It's either
cardiac chest pain
or ischemic, possible
cardiac chest pain or
non-cardiac chest pain.
So as we said, we have
a patient with chest
pain and the next
thing we want to do is
gather more details
and kind of construct
an HPI. As clinicians,
we should really
attempt to elicit more
information using the
LOPQRST acronym that
we all learned in DPR.
And for now, just
try and focus on the
important aspects of
our patient's HPI.
You can read it on
your own, but as you
do, also try to think
of some differentials
and remember to
keep them broad.
So on this slide,
I've listed out some
important differentials
that you should
be keeping in the
back of your mind when
someone presents
to your office with
the chief complaint of
chest pain. Starting
with psychogenic,
you could be thinking
maybe it's a pang
disorder, right?
But these patients
will present with
palpations, sweating,
trembling, shaking,
shortness of breath,
maybe feeling a
choking. You might
think somatic symptom
disorder, right? An
excessive thought,
feeling, or behaviors
about symptoms
like an anxiety,
frequent doctor visits.
Usually the symptoms
vary, but the stress
is really persistent
and usually goes on
for greater than six
months. You could
also be thinking illness,
anxiety disorder,
right, a preoccupation
with having or
requiring a serious
illness. But again,
that's also going to
be going on for six
months or greater.
Moving on to pulmonary,
maybe we're thinking
pulmonary embolism,
right, a sudden
onset difficulty
breathing. With pulmonary
embolism, you're
going to have
pleuritic chest pain.
The patient might be
coughing up blood.
Usually with someone
who presents with a
pulmonary embolism on
boards. The classic
presentation is a
patient that's post-op,
has a long travel
history or a recent
long immobilization,
right, flying in a
plane, could be taking
oral contraceptives,
could be pregnant,
history of cancer.
Maybe you're thinking,
I don't know,
pneumothorax, right? Again,
for the boards, you're
going to see a young,
tall, thin male for
a spontaneous pneumothorax,
or in a trauma
patient, you're going
to see a tension
pneumothorax, and these
patients can present with
sudden onset unilateral
chest pain, shortness
of breath, but on
exam they're going to
have decreased breath
sounds on the affected
side. Maybe you're also
thinking pneumonia,
right? But in pneumonia
you're going to
see fevers, productive
coughing, maybe called
sputum. The patient's
going to be fatigued.
You're going to
probably want to do an x
-ray. You'll see lobar
consolidation or maybe
a cavitary lesion.
If you do labs you're
going to have an
increased white blood cell
count with a left
shift or neutrophilia.
Moving on to musculoskeletal
system, right?
Maybe this is just a simple
case of costochondritis
right always think
about that on your
list usually these
are more sharp chest
pain which is localized
to the costal sternal
or costochondral joints
and pain is worse
with movement right
twisting reaching uh but
however the key
difference here is that
patients with costochondritis
are going to have
reproducible pain with
palpation and that
helps you rule out any
cardiac causes there's
also something called
triat syndrome which
is very similar to
costochondritis but
this actually includes
visible swelling over
the joint. Moving on
to gastrointestinal
maybe we're thinking GERD
right heartburn you'll
usually have a burning
sensation behind
the sternum might have
regurgitation or a
sour or bitter taste in
your mouth and especially
these symptoms happen
when lying down.
The chest discomfort
can mimic angina but
it's not exertional
right they're not having
these symptoms when
they exert themselves
going up and down the
stairs doing exercise.
However, in GERD,
these symptoms are
reproducible by the
posture or food, right?
Worse than when laying
down or bending over.
Symptoms might be after
eating, especially
eating like large
fatty acidic
meals, and they
usually go away with
antacids or proton
pump inhibitors, PPI.
Maybe you're thinking
esophageal dysphagia,
right? Patients
usually have difficulty
swallowing or a
sensation of food getting
stuck in their mouth.
Maybe you're thinking
gastritis, right?
Epigastric pain or
discomfort, nausea,
vomiting, loss of appetite.
Let's see.
Maybe you're thinking
peptic ulcer disease,
right? Epigastric pain,
and again, burning,
gnawing, and it's
usually worsened by food
and relieved with antacids.
Sometimes in peptic
ulcer disease, you
might see blood in the
stool or blood in the
*****. Maybe you're
also thinking pancreatitis
right a severe
constant epigastric pain
but with patients with
pancreatitis the pain
is often described as
radiating straight to
the back and worsened
when lying supine and
improved when leaning
forward and pancreatitis
you can also see
signs like fever
cullen sign which is a
periumbilical bruising
gray turner sign which is
flank bruising so
just keep all these
differentials in mind
moving on to last but not
least the cardiac symptoms
right so this could
be stable angina which
is usually described
as substernal chest
pressure tightness
heaviness and usually
triggered by exertion
emotional stress cold and
relieved with the rest
of nitroglycerin
maybe you're thinking
pericarditis right it's
usually pleuritic pain
better with leaning
forward and you would
also hear a friction rub
on auscultation maybe
you're thinking aortic
dissection right
sudden severe often
described as a tearing chest
or back pain and the
classic patient will
be seen with a history
of like hypertension
and it's very very
common on the boards they
also love aortic
dissections in patients
like connective tissue
diseases such as marfans
ellerdanlos lastly heart
failure maybe we're
thinking heart failure
right but you also
be on your differential
right you would see
orthopnea or dyspnea
when lying flat fatigue
you can hear pulmonary
crackles possibly
an s3 gallop or an s4
but you also notice
peripheral edema or
jugular venous distension.
So all of these symptoms
could sound like our
patient, right? And
it's always good to
keep in mind a very
broad range of ideas when
it comes to a patient
presenting with chest
pain because we don't
always want to go straight
to cardiac because as
you can see there's
so many other causes
of chest discomfort.
If we look at this
next slide I illustrate
the index of suspicion
that chest pain is
ischemic in origin. So
on the left you have
symptoms such as
central chest pain,
pressure, squeezing,
gripping. These all give
a high probability of
ischemia. And on the
right you will see
symptoms on the lower
end that are considered
likely non-cardiac
chest pain. Symptoms
like fleeting pain,
shifting pain, pleuritic
pain. Those are
also most likely not
ischemic in nature.
On this slide I just
want to take time to
talk about women with
chest pain. Many of
you have probably
heard women can present
differently with chest
pain. A large percentage
of MIs in women may
go unrecognized.
And in a study of over
90,000 people, the
prevalence of unrecognized
MI was shown to
be higher in women
than men at 30% versus
16%. Therefore, women
face a delay in diagnosis,
and particularly
those of younger ages
or in women with
diabetes. Although there
are more similarities
in how women and men
present with ischemic
heart disease than
differences, the
likelihood of presenting
without chest pain in
ischemic heart disease
is greater in women
than men. Women are
more likely than men
to have chest pain
induced by rest, sleep,
mental stress. And in
addition, women are
also more likely to
present with accompanying
systems like fatigue,
shortness of breath,
nausea, vomiting.
So going back to our
patient vignette, I
wanted to point out
some key symptoms
you should be aware
of, right? Our patient
presents with crushing
chest pain in the
middle of the chest.
The pain is exacerbated
when they go up
the stairs and the
pain is relieved
with breaths. So more
likely than not, we
can comfortably say
that the chest pain
is cardiac in nature.
So like I've been
saying, this lecture is
going to focus on
ischemic heart disease,
specifically stable and
vasospastic angina. So
let's start with stable
angina. Most importantly,
what you need to know
and remember from
this slide is stable
angina is usually
secondary to atherosclerosis
and occludes greater
than 70% of a coronary
artery and that
greater than 70%
occlusion of the coronary
artery leads to symptoms
of angina. Again, there
is an atherosclerotic
plaque that's building
up and it's going to
occlude, I say again,
greater than 70% of
the coronary artery.
The typical patient
with stable angina is
usually a man greater
than 50 years or a woman
greater than 60 years
of age who complains
of episodes of chest
discomfort usually
described as a heaviness
pressure squeezing
smothering or choking
and only rarely just as
frank chest pain when
the patient is asked
to localize the
sensation they typically
place a hand over the
sternum sometimes with
a clenched fist to indicate
a squeezing central
substernal discomfort
and this is known
as levine sign typically
these symptoms last
no more than 10 minutes
and can radiate to
either shoulder and
to both arms. It also
can arise in or radiate
to the back, interscapular
region, root of the
neck, jaw, teeth,
epigastrum, and angina
is rarely localized
below the umbilicus
or above the mandible.
Episodes of angina
typically are caused by
exertion, either
exercise, hurrying, ******
activity, or they're
caused by emotions,
stress, anger, fright,
frustration, and are
relieved by rest and
sublingual nitroglycerin.
Again, stable angina
only occurs with
provocation therefore
you need exertion or an
emotional stressor
to elicit the anginal
symptoms and without
provocation the patient has
no symptoms comparatively
to unstable angina
where you don't need
exertion and the
pain is present at rest
so again stable angina
is exertional angina
typically relieved in
one to five minutes
by slowing or ceasing
activity and even more
rapidly by rest and
sublingual nitroglycerin
the way I like to
think of stable angina
I like to break down
the word stable angina
stable being a patient
is stable at rest
and compare this to
unstable angina where
they are unstable at rest
focusing on the
pathophysiology of stable
angina we should talk
about perfusion demand
mismatch so perfusion
is the blood delivered
or the oxygen supply
and the demand is the
blood needed or the
oxygen demand there are
four major factors that
determine myocardial
work and therefore
myocardial oxygen demand
is determined by heart
rate systolic blood
pressure myocardial wall
tension and myocardial
contractility on the
other side oxygen
supply is determined by
three things coronary
artery blood flow
hemoglobin concentration
and oxygen unloading at
rest the blood supply
can meet the oxygen
demand of the heart.
However, during
exertion, the heart's
demand for oxygen
increases, but supply
cannot keep up. This
creates what we call
a perfusion demand
mismatch. And this
is often due to that
greater than 70%
blockage in the coronary
artery. At rest,
the blood supply is
usually adequate to
meet the heart's
oxygen needs. However,
with exertion factors
such as increased
heart rate, contractility,
preload or afterload
topics you may have
already covered in
your physiology or
cardiology lectures,
drive oxygen demand
higher. On the supply
side, atherosclerotic
plaque significantly
narrows that vessel's
lumen, limiting the
blood flow and oxygen
delivery. The result
is a transient myocardial
ischemia during
periods of increased
activity, which resolves
with rest when demand
decreases and supply
can once again meet
the heart's needs.
Now let's pivot to
vasospastic angina, also
known as Prinsmetall
angina. In 1959, Dr.
Prinsmettl published a
landmark paper in the
American Journal of
Medicine titled Angina
Pectoris 1, a variant
form of angina pectoris
preliminary report. In
this, he described a
distinct form of chest
pain that was caused
by spasm of a coronary
artery rather than
fixed atherosclerotic
obstruction, was associated
with transient ST
segment elevations on
ECG, indicating
transmural ischemia, and
occurred at rest rather
than with exertion,
which differentiates
it from stable angina.
Because of this unique
mechanism and presentation,
the condition became
to be known as Prinz
metal variant angina,
or simply Prinz metal
angina, but now we just
call it vasospastic
angina. In this
condition, the coronary
arteries suddenly spasm,
narrowing the vessel
and restricting blood
flow. Common triggers
include *******, a
potent vasoconstrictor,
alcohol, and certain
medications such as
triptans, for example,
sumatriptan, which
you'll learn more about
in Dr. Goldstein's
lecture. The pathophysiology
for vasospastic
angina is brief. You
have an artery that
spasm, causing decreased
blood flow, and
reduces oxygen delivery
to the myocardium, which
gives you those
classic angina-like
symptoms. The treatment
focuses on relieving
these spasms and preventing
reoccurrence, and
includes calcium channel
blockers, nitrates,
and smoking cessation
when applicable.
Back to the vignette.
Now think about what
test would you want to
run on this patient?
Just take a minute,
think about things
that you've heard
about in the past, and
then we'll discuss
it in the next slide.
As far as a comprehensive
workup is concerned,
just like with any
patient, we should
really begin with a good
history and physical.
So looking at the
history, you might notice
things like the chest
pain is characterized
by diffuse discomfort
that may be difficult
to localize. The
patient often indicates
the entire chest
when asked whether
discomfort is felt. The
intensity of discomfort
increases and
decreases over several
minutes, and termination
of the provoking
factors such as stopping
activity and resting
may make symptoms feel
better. On the other
hand, activities in
situations that increase
myocardial oxygen
demand, like physical
activity, the cold,
emotional stress,
****** ***********, may
make the pain worse.
Angina is usually
characterized more as a
discomfort rather than
pain and often radiates
to the shoulders,
arms, wrists, fingers,
neck, and throat,
lower jaw, and teeth,
and upper abdomen, and
rarely to the back.
You might have the
patient describe the
pain generally lasting
for two to five
minutes, but no more
than 10 minutes. You
should also ask the
patient about some
associated symptoms,
such as any shortness
of breath, nausea,
sweating, fatigue,
dizziness,
lightheadedness.
Moving on to past
medical history, patients
may have a medical
history pertinent for
cardiovascular risk
factors and or other types
of vascular disease,
such as a ******,
peripheral vascular
disease. Many patients who
are ultimately diagnosed
with myocardial
ischemia have key
pieces of information in
their social and family
histories too. For
example, family history
may reveal members with
********* cardiovascular
disease or
hypertrophic cardiomyopathy,
and patients may admit
to unhealthy diets,
sedentary lifestyle,
and like we said before,
cigarette smoking.
The physical exam
also might just be
normal because the
pain is only felt
with exertion,
so if they're not
exerting themselves
in office, you
may not have any
current chest pain.
As far as lab tests
go, no matter who the
patient is, anyone
you see in office that
presents you with
chest pain is going to
get an ECG and a chest
x-ray. The ECG is
not going to show any
baseline changes at
rest because, again,
the symptoms only
come on with exertion.
The chest x-ray will
most likely be normal,
but sometimes you
may find in a large
cardiac silhouette,
but that's not really
diagnostic for stable
angina. You can run
cardiac biomarkers like
troponins or CKMB,
but again, they are
going to be normal,
right? You don't really
want to worry too much
about the intricacies
of the troponins and
the CKMB so far. Dr.
Narod will cover them
more in part two. So
I'm not really going
to harp on them too
much now, but just
understand that in a patient
with stable angina,
they're going to be
normal. And if you
run, let's say a lipid
panel, you might see
some elevated LDL or a
decrease in HDL like
we discussed before.
So now the big
question is, what else
can we do, right?
The physical is
normal, the lab's
normal. So what does
it take to diagnose
stable angina?
And if you said a
stress test, then you're
correct. In 2021, the
AHA and the ACC released
their first ever
standalone chest pain
guideline, which included
a clear algorithmic
flowchart to help you
determine who should
undergo stress testing.
The process starts
with a structured
pretest probability
assessment, which
takes into account the
patient's age, ***, chest
pain characteristics,
and categorizes them
into low, intermediate,
or intermediate high
risks. From there,
the schematic kind of
helps guide which type
of stress test is most
appropriate, but don't
worry about them too
much. You don't need
to memorize this entire
algorithm. For now,
just focus on understanding
what the options
are and how the
general approach works.
So here's another flow
chart created by Dr.
Murad that uses a risk
assessment tool based
on the patient's
pretest probability of
coronary artery disease.
Patients classified
as low risk generally
do not need a stress
test. Patients with
high risk, such as those
with known coronary
artery disease who are
already on medications
but still have
symptoms, they just go
straight to the cath lab.
There's no need for a
stress test in their
cases. In the intermediate
risk patients,
those are the ones
that are most likely to
benefit from stress
testing. Again, don't
stress about memorizing
every detail right now.
Just understand that
different risk categories
lead to different
management options.
Once the decision
is made to pursue a
stress test, the next
step is choosing the
right stress test.
Key questions to ask
include can the patient
exercise adequately?
Is the resting ECG
normal? Does the
patient have a large
body habitus or lung
disease that might
be affecting imaging?
In general, we'll use
an exercise stress
test most of the time.
However, the patient
cannot exercise.
For example, due to
osteoarthritis, rheumatoid
arthritis, advanced
age, fragility, high
fall risk, we opt for
the pharmacological
stress test instead.
Next, we need to
decide which evaluation
method to pair with
the stress test.
Technically, any evaluation
method can be used
with any type of
stress test. However,
echocardiograms and
radionucleotide imaging
are most often paired
with pharmacological
stress tests, while
ECG monitoring is
typically paired with
exercise stress testing.
Now let's take a closer
look at the exercise
stress test. This is
the most commonly used
form of stress testing
most often performed
on a treadmill. It's
popular because it's
simple and expensive
and well-validated.
The patient walks or
runs on the treadmill
aiming for a target
heart rate about 85% of
their predicted maximum
while being continuously
monitored with an
ECG, and the goal is
to reproduce and
document that transient
myocardial ischemia. As
we discussed earlier,
exercise increases the
heart's oxygen demand
in the presence of
significant atherosclerosis.
However, the blood
supply can't keep
up, leading to transient
ischemia, which we
can then capture on
the ECG. A positive
stress test is typically
indicated by ST segment
depression or T-wave
inversions. And some
reasons to stop include
chest discomfort,
severe shortness
of breath,
dizziness, severe
fatigue, or a drop
in systolic blood
pressure greater
than 10 millimeters
of mercury.
Other changes such as
T-wave abnormalities,
conjunction
disturbances, or
ventricular arrhythmias
should be noted if
they occur during
exercise, but they
are just not diagnostic
on their own.
On this slide, I just
wanted to show you
what an ST-segment
depression and a T-wave
inversion look like.
On the top left, you
see an example in the
ST-segment depression,
something you can
now connect back
to your ECG lectures,
but here you see it
more in a context of
a clinical syndrome.
On the bottom right,
we have a T-wave
inversion. Notice
that in the normal
image, the T-wave
points upward, while in
the bottom image,
it flips downward,
and that's what we
call the inversion.
Both of these are
abnormal findings on
an ECG during an
exercise stress test.
Now, for patients who
can't exercise, have
baseline ECG abnormalities
that make interpretation
unreliable, or had
a prior exercise
ECG that was non-diagnostic
due to inadequate
heart rate response, we
can use a pharmacological
stress test. This
is just another well
-validated option for
evaluating patients
who require a stress
test, and it tends to be
more sensitive and
specific compared to
exercise ECGs alone,
although it is more costly.
These are most commonly
performed using
dobutamine or adenosine.
From a board exam
perspective, you
should know your drug
contraindications, right?
For example, can you give
adenosine to a patient
with asthma? No. Why?
Because although
adenosine causes
vasodilation, it also
triggers bronchoconstriction,
making it
contraindicated in
asthma. In such,
patients like that
would then require
dobutamine instead.
Regardless of the
agent, though, the goal
is the same. It's to
achieve a target heart
rate of about 85% of
the predicted maximum,
and a positive test
is usually indicated
by dyskinesias or
abnormal ventricular
wall motion observed
on the echocardiogram.
On this slide, I just
want to illustrate an
example of abnormal
ventricular wall
movement that you can
see on an echocardiogram.
On the left, we have
normal ventricular
wall movement, and on
the right, we can see
wall motion abnormalities
seen on an echo.
So going back to our
patient, I added a
little blurb on the
bottom. For physical
exam it was all
within normal limits.
For the labs the
LDL was slightly
elevated. The HDL was
around 40 which is
slightly decreased and
the physician decides
to perform an
exercise stress test.
And now I have a
follow-up question.
So which of the
following EKG
changes would
denote a positive
exercise stress test
on this patient?
Stop for a quick
second think
about it and in
a second we'll
come back and
take a look at it.
So the correct answer
is ST segment depression
and actually if
you go back a few
slides you'll see that
I noted that a positive
stress test is
indicated by either ST
segment depressions
or T wave inversions.
So now let's move on
to management. Once
ischemic heart disease
is diagnosed the plan
must be individualized
right medicine is
never a one size fits
all so we broke this up
into six different
steps for management the
first thing is education
reassurance emphasize
that this is not a
terminal disease and
the patient can still
enjoy life with proper
management for two
you want to identify
or treat some aggravating
conditions right
manage their left
ventricular hypertrophy
look for valvular
disease hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy maybe they
have hyperthyroidism or
anemia you can look at
lifestyle modifications
right change their
diet up less trans
and saturated fats more
leafy greens you can
tell them to gradually
increase their physical
conditioning and
big one is smoking
cessation and this is
very very important like
we discussed before you
also want to control
for risk factors
right if they have
hypertension or diabetes
we can treat their
hypertension or diabetes.
For diabetes, we can
give them SGLT2 inhibitors
or GLP-1 receptor
agonist. We might want
to give them lipids
for the dyslipidemia
and then address the
obesity as needed. For
medical therapy, it's
broken up again. We
want to prevent angina,
so we give them beta
blockers, calcium
channel blockers, which
I'll talk about in a
couple slides. For
acute symptom relief,
remember I was talking
about nitrates. Those
will relieve the symptoms
of stable angina.
There's also different
ones that I mentioned
before too, preventing
disease progression.
You have your
antiplatelet therapy, your
lipid lowering therapy,
your ACEs, your ARBs,
SGLT2 inhibitors, or
your GLP-1 agonist.
And last but not
least, we'll talk about
revascularization. So
there's two different
options. There's
usually a percutaneous
coronary intervention
or PCI, or there's
a coronary artery
bypass graft or a
CABG, which we'll talk
about very shortly.
I just want to spend
time to talk about a
couple of the drugs
mentioned in the previous
slide except I'm just
not going to delve
too deep into them
because Goldstein is
probably giving you
lectures on these already.
So beta blockers are
the first line treatment
for reducing angina
episodes. The propanolol
was actually the
first clinically used
beta blocker. It's
non-selective but now
cardioselective agents
like atenolol and metoporol
are now preferred as
they avoid interfering
with bronchodilation
and peripheral
vasodilation. How do
they work? They work by
lowering the heart rate,
reducing contractility,
and lowering blood
pressure and afterload,
which all decrease
the oxygen demand, but
they also can increase
the diastolic filling
time, which in turn
increases oxygen
supply. Beyond symptom
control, beta blockers
improve survival in
patients with prior MIs
or systolic heart failure,
but very important,
do not use beta blockers
in patients with
vasospastic angina
calcium channel blockers
can be used as monotherapy
and stable angina
when beta blockers
are not suitable due
to poor response adverse
effect the history
of asthma copd conduction
disorders vasospastic
angina or symptomatic
peripheral arterial
disease their first
line for vasospastic
angina you have your
non-dihydropyridines
your verapamil or
deltiazam. And how these
work is again, they
decrease the heart rate,
they decrease the
myocardial contractility
to ultimately decrease
the oxygen demand, but
then they also increase
coronary vasodilation,
which in turn increases
oxygen supply.
Sublingual nitroglycerin
is a therapy
of choice for acute
anginal episodes.
It works within
about two to five
minutes and usually
lasts 15 to 30.
Tolerance isn't an
issue with intermittent
use, even in patients
with chronic nitrate
therapy. The usual
recommendation is one dose
every five minutes
for up to three doses,
then call EMS if symptoms
persist. Its main
effect is venous
vasodilation, which
decreases preload,
reduces wall stress, and
lowers myocardial
oxygen demand. At higher
doses, it also causes
mild atrial dilation,
which decreases afterload,
and coronary artery
vasodilation, which
can help and variant
angina. Side effects
can include headache,
flushing, hypotension,
and again for the
boards it's important to
never use PDE5 inhibitors
such as sidenafil,
tadalafil, fredenafil
because both increase
cyclic GMP leading
to profound potentially
fatal hypotension.
In the absence of
contraindications all
patients with ischemic
heart disease should
receive aspirin. It
reduces the risk of MI,
******, and vascular
death in patients with
prior cardiovascular
events. The optimal
dose for secondary
prevention is unclear, but
usually it's about
75 to 162 mg per day.
Higher doses may be used
in certain patients.
Aspirin we know
irreversibly inhibits COX-1
and COX-2, blocking
platelet aggregation and
reducing thrombus
risk. The main concern
with chronic use is major
bleeding, especially
with GI bleeding. For
patients who cannot
take aspirin or have
prior GI bleeding,
clopidogrel is actually
a reasonable alternative,
and we know that it
irreversibly blocks
the PTY-12 ADP receptor
on platelets, preventing
aggregation and
fibrogen cross-linking.
All patients with
ischemic heart disease
should be started on
lifelong high-intensity
statin therapy as well,
either torvastatin,
40-80 mg, or rosuvastatin,
20-40 mg, regardless
of baseline LDL. LDL
is a main driver of
plaque buildup and
high intensity statins
lower LDL by around
greater than 50% Which
slows the disease and
sometimes reverses plaques
And by reducing the
plaques, we're going
to reduce the heart
attack and ****** risk
They also stabilize
plaques, making them less
likely to rupture
Before starting, check
a lipid panel and liver
enzymes and monitor
for muscle pain or
liver dysfunction If
symptoms arise, take
labs like a CK or liver
function test those
should be checked before.
When stable ischemic
heart disease is
first diagnosed we
start with optimal
medical therapy as
discussed earlier.
Revascularization
is considered
for unstable
disease, intractable
symptoms, high
-risk anatomy,
patients with diabetes,
impaired left ventricular
function, but it's
always in addition to
risk factor control
and medical management,
never instead of.
Here's an algorithm
before you which shows
how these decisions
kind of fit together.
But again, don't worry
about this flow chart.
Just understand the
general principles.
Now let's move on to
revascularization. The
first method of
revascularization is called
percutaneous coronary
intervention or PCI,
which is a common
option for patients with
symptom limiting
angina that persists
despite medical therapy,
usually in case of one
or two vessel disease.
Again, this is in
the case of one to two
vessel disease. In PCI,
a catheter is threaded
through an artery
usually the femoral
artery and up to the
coronary vessel where
it's then a balloon is
inflated at the site
of the narrowing to
open up the artery and
a drug eluding stent is
placed to keep it open
these stents usually
have greatly improved
long-term outcomes
after pci patients are
placed on dual anti
-platelet therapies so
aspirin indefinitely
and a pty12 inhibitor
like clopidogrel
for at least 12 months
to reduce the risk
of stent thrombosis
and the results are
impressive. Over 95%
of patients experience
effective relief
of angina symptoms.
The second method is
coronary artery bypass
grafting or CABG for
short. It's used for
patients with severe
stenosis in two or three
major coronary arteries,
again in two or
three major coronary
arteries, especially when
there's clear evidence
of myocardial ischemia.
It's particularly
recommended for those
with three vessel
disease plus diabetes or
reduced left ventricular
function, or for
certain two-vessel cases
involving the LAD with
diabetes or left
ventricular dysfunction.
In CABG, surgeons
create a new route for
blood to flow around
the blockage, often
using internal mammary
arteries or the radial
artery, and if
arteries aren't usually
suitable, sometimes
they'll use the saphenous
vein grafts from the
leg. After complete
revascularization,
about 90% of patients
have major relief
from angina symptoms.
Here I created a
table. Again, don't get
too bogged down with
the details. Just
understand that PCI
is used for a single
to two vessel disease
when a cabbage
is used for two or
three vessel disease.
So again, this is
our last question. If
you want to read it
on your own, go ahead
and then we'll move
on to the answer.
Before I show you the
answer, I just want
to again point out
some key words in
here. It says on stress
testing, the patient
develops ST segment
depressions in leads
1 and AVL, and these
indicate ST depressions
in one vessel at
about 85% of her
maximal heart rate.
So what would be the
best appropriate next
step in management?
Why don't you pause
the recording,
think about it, and then
we'll come back
to the answer.
And if you said choice
B, you would be correct.
Again, this is one
vessel, so therefore
we're going to use a
PCI as the intervention
of choice. Again
this lecture is in
combination with the part
two lecture and you're
going to learn more about
ST segment depressions
and certain leads
on EKG. Just know
that for one vessel
we're going to use a PCI.
I created a summary
table with the
key aspects to know
for stable angina
versus vasospastic
angina and then I
took this straight
from first aid if
you would like to
read it as well.
As always if you
have any questions
please feel free
to email either Dr.
Murad or myself
and we'd be more
than happy to answer
the questions as
well as leave some
feedback for us.
Here's the link
for the feedback.
Last but not least
I just want to thank
you all for your time.
I hope you enjoy my
lecture and I'll see
you all very soon.